<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise, maintaining that temporall blessings are to bee sought and asked with submission to the will of God Wherein is confuted the presumptious way of absolute praying for temporals, in the particulars, broached, and defended by Mr. Rice Boye, in a late pamphlet, intituled The importunate beggar. As also a discovery of the late dangerous errours of Mr. Iohn Traske, and most of his strange assertions. Both necessary to be knowne of all for the avoiding of the like errours, and continuing in the truth. By Edw: Norice.</title>
            <author>Norris, Edward, 1584-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18646</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103140</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838897</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838897</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3287</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08319)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3287)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1212:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise, maintaining that temporall blessings are to bee sought and asked with submission to the will of God Wherein is confuted the presumptious way of absolute praying for temporals, in the particulars, broached, and defended by Mr. Rice Boye, in a late pamphlet, intituled The importunate beggar. As also a discovery of the late dangerous errours of Mr. Iohn Traske, and most of his strange assertions. Both necessary to be knowne of all for the avoiding of the like errours, and continuing in the truth. By Edw: Norice.</title>
                  <author>Norris, Edward, 1584-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 168 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Augustine Mathewes] for Robert Milbourne at the Vnicorne neere Fleet bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Boye, Rice.  The importunate begger for things necessary.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC addendum.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A treatise on the fourth petition.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Traske, John, d. ca. 1638 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Boye, Rice. --  Importunate begger for things necessary --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="license">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3287:1"/>
                  <p>Perlegi Tractatum hunc, &amp; dignum exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ut Typis mandetur.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>THO: WEEKES R. P. Epiſc. Lond. Cap. Domeſt.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3287:1"/>
                  <p>A TREATISE, MAINTAINING that <hi>Temporall Bleſsings</hi> are to bee ſought and asked with ſubmiſſion <hi>to the will of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherein is Confuted the Preſumptuous way of abſolute praying for <hi>Temporals,</hi> in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, broached, and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Mr. <hi>Rice Boye,</hi> in a late Pamphlet, Intituled <hi>The Importunate Beggar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As alſo a Diſcovery of the late dangerous errours of Mr. <hi>Iohn Traske,</hi> and moſt of his ſtrange Aſſertions.</p>
                  <p>Both neceſſary to be knowne of all for the avoiding of the like errours, and continuing in the Truth</p>
                  <p>By EDW: NORICE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Milbourne</hi> at the Vnicorne neere Fleet bridge. 1636.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3287:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3287:2"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader,</hi> It is ſo that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 7. yeares ſithence, there aroſe an opinion in the Weſterne parts, that men are to pray for temporall things in as abſolute a manner as for ſpirituall, and that the promiſes are alike: one of the chiefe broachers of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb facs="tcp:3287:3"/>(being a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>) comes to me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame was publikly known, and craftily demands of me, whether we may not abſolutely pray unto <hi>God</hi> for bread, &amp; depend upon his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for neceſſaries; to which I anſwered, that I conceived wee might and ought: ſhortly after I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that there was more in the matter, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3287:3"/>that under bread and neceſſaries, they inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, health, life, food, raiment, good ſucceſſe in affaires, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conveniences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to our ſelves, or others; with this rule and poſition that whoſoever did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſhould certainly obtaine thoſe things in the particular, and if any did not, it was becauſe they wanted<note n="*" place="margin">He pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the faith of miracles to continu ſtil. And that all which dyed of the plague wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted faith.</note> 
                     <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3287:4"/>
                  <p>Hereupon were the <hi>conſciences</hi> of many people, that lay under ſome outward afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (as poverty, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of themſelves or theirs, il ſucceſſe, &amp;c.) much diſquietted and troubled, being char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by them with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe in their praiers (as ſome of them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed) &amp; making their moan concerning the ſame, I was intreated to deliver ſome <hi>grouds</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3287:4"/>in publicke about the point, &amp; to lay down directions co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning a right maner of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral things, that they might know whereupon to ſettle themſelves, and their practiſe: This upon requeſt (there being yet no open conteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) I was willing to do; and taking a ſtem upon a Feſtival, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to that purpoſe <hi>the fourth Petition of the
<pb facs="tcp:3287:5"/>Lords Prayer,</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring therin certain <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments</hi> againſt ſuch kind of abſolute pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>outward things,</hi> and defending the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon received <hi>doctrine</hi> of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and all other Churches.</p>
                  <p>VVhereat under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſhortly after how much hee was diſpleaſed, I copyed out my <hi>Arguments,</hi> and ſent them to him;
<pb facs="tcp:3287:5"/>vvhereupon he ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad a large <hi>diſcourſe</hi> of the point, declaring upon vvhat Grounds they held their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and with vvhat cautions of <hi>repentance</hi> &amp; <hi>love,</hi> aſvvell as <hi>faith.</hi> And not long after (as I remember) an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to my five <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> inveighing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vvhere againſt me, and my Sermon, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with his <hi>anſwere</hi> to me, ſharp <hi>Invectives</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3287:6"/>againſt me, for vvhat I had done and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; vvhich letters I have by mee yet to ſhew, ful of reproach. Hereupon I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to extract cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of his groſſeſt <hi>Aſſertions,</hi> and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to the vievv of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that they might ſee vvhat <hi>Doctrine</hi> was taught, and ſecretly vented a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their people:
<pb facs="tcp:3287:6"/>vvarning him vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, not to make any publike <hi>Controverſie</hi> in the Church, in regard of the law forbidding the ſame, &amp; admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing him further by private Letters of his errour, &amp; evill dealing with me After which he was privatly &amp; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly dealt withall, by divers learned and able <hi>Miniſters,</hi> labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to convince him, but all in vaine; for
<pb facs="tcp:3287:7"/>in ſtead of hearkning to their counſell, hee reproached their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with vaunts and brags, as hee had uſed me before, and was ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reforming this opinion, that hee ran out into an other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of <hi>Separation,</hi> diſclaiming utterly of the Church, or any Communion with it. I then ſeeing the man to be ſo wilfull in his wayes, medled no
<pb facs="tcp:3287:7"/>more in this poynt, but (having ſatisfied many) gave it over, and ſo it hath reſted theſe five yeares, or thereabouts.</p>
                  <p>Now after all this time (being it ſeemes in love with his olde conceits) he hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably printed by ſtealth al thoſe former paſſages: the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> of his <hi>Opinion;</hi> my <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments</hi> with their <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers;</hi> the <hi>extract</hi> of his
<pb facs="tcp:3287:8"/>
                     <hi>Aſſertions,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>It was,</hi> Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erilis the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologia.</note> ſtiling it my <hi>Proſopopeia;</hi> and his <hi>diſtinction</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> into <hi>Eternall,</hi> and <hi>Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> intituling the ſame, <hi>The importunat Beggar;</hi> vvhich hee hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlarded with many foule ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy imputations, and bitter invectives, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring me, and other <hi>Miniſters</hi> that dealt with him, to <hi>Jannes</hi> &amp; <hi>Jambres,</hi> with thoſe <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian jugglers</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:3287:8"/>withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ſuch like ſtuffe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is full. And this he doth under prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that I had again refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie as much as before; whereas it cannot be proved, neither can I poſsibly reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that I have at all medled with the controverſie wellneers theſe five yeares, but had almoſt forgotten it.</p>
                  <p>Being thus unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily
<pb facs="tcp:3287:9"/>dealth withall, I thought it neceſſarie for the vindicating of my ſelfe, but chiefly of the <hi>Truth</hi> from his ſlanders (if leave may be given) to returne ſome anſwere to his <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> &amp; to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine &amp; confirme the ancient received Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and uſuall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in this behalfe; to which purpoſe, I conceived it beſt to publiſh the
<pb facs="tcp:3287:9"/>Sermon it ſelfe, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my briefe <hi>Notes</hi>) and withall, by way of <hi>Explication,</hi> to defend the truth of my Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts againſt his Replies &amp; Anſwers, as they lie in order, that all may ſee &amp; ſo judge of what was then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, and is ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by me. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in admoniſhing the <hi>Reader</hi> firſt of theſe few things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That in my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,
<pb facs="tcp:3287:10"/>I ſtile him not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch fully the <hi>Boy,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his name; nor yet the <hi>Beggar,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the title of his booke, as I might have done; but rather the <hi>Temporary,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his ſingular o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of a <hi>Temporary faith,</hi> as beſt ſuiting with the matter in hand, and the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his building.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That in my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, (vvhich I little
<pb facs="tcp:3287:10"/>thought ſhould haue bin made ſo publike) I gathered ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento, &amp; handled all in ſuch a manner, as the time of <hi>Preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> would afford, &amp; was moſt agreeable to the quality of the Audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> courſe I have followed in this <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> being chiefly to deale with ſuch, and not with any of the Learneder ſort,<note place="margin">For which cauſe I cite thoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors as are moſt familiar.</note> as knowing none intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled
<pb facs="tcp:3287:11"/>with the errour.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That in my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, I have indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured as to avoid his ſcurrility, a thing not imitable: ſo alſo not to trace him in all his vvandring Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, vvhich vvere end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: but rather to anſwer plainly to the poynt and matter, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the reſt to vaniſh as a myſt, the light of Trueth comming in place: vvhich I ſpeak
<pb facs="tcp:3287:11"/>to prevent any more ſlanders of his (if it may bee) that I have not anſwered his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, or miſ-tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed his Writings, becauſe I have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed every imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent ſpeech, or idle paſſage in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which I held needleſſe, but onely the ſubſtance of his Doctrine &amp; drift, as hee defendeth it in his Booke; vvherein I have not wronged
<pb facs="tcp:3287:12"/>him (that I know) a ſyllable. And thus <hi>Reader,</hi> commending all to the bleſsing of God, and thy ſelfe to his grace, praying that we may all be guided by a right Spirit, I remaine</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine in, and for the Lord, and his Truth. <hi>Envv. Norice.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3287:12"/>
                  <head>A TREATISE, MAINTAINING, that Temporall Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings are to bee ſought and asked, with ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>to the will of God,</hi> as it is in the fourth Petition,</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <p>Give us this day our daily bread.</p> 
                        <bibl>Math. 6.11.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Lord JESUS CHRIST, the great Shepherd of the Flocke, hath left no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unſaid or undone,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3287:13"/>that may ſerve for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction or comfort of his people, and therefore knowing how neceſſary Prayer is for the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the ſame (being his owne Ordinance) hath left them direction for that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, how it ought to be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, with what Petitions, and to what ends, and that not onely by divers ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and paſſages occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally uttered to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but by a forme and frame of prayer purpoſely made to give them directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therein, commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Lords Prayer,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſumme of all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3287:13"/>lawfull petitions, and the order of them. Now theſe wordes are a part of the ſame, and containe the fourth Petition, or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall requeſt, as they are reckoned in order; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning outward things, or the matters of this life, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary to be known, for our better direction in the ſeeking of ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at the hands of God. The matter then deſired, according to the letter, is Bread, and that for the day; whereby is meant, all the abſolute neceſſaries of this life, as bread, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what anſwerable unto it, is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3287:14"/>abſolutely neceſſary (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the meanes) for the preſervation of the life of man; whence the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo often mentions the ſame as the chiefe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.20. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 25.29. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for that errour of ſuperſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial conceited by ſome out of the originall, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to the Sacrament, &amp;c. I meddle not with it, being ſufficiently confuted<note n="*" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Scudder.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, vel <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Luk. 11.2.</note> by others. By <hi>Daily,</hi> is meant that which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for the day, or for the time preſent, without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſollicitude: ſo that in ſumme, maintenance for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3287:14"/>life is here deſired, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we conſider for our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe, three things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Who may hopefully and warrantably aske out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things at the hands of God, and that is ſuch as have firſt ſought heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things of God, as their Father; from the Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</item>
                     <item>2. On what termes, and by what claime they may aske outward things, and that is, onely as a gift, <hi>Give us.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. In what quantity and meaſure thoſe things are to bee ſought, that is, ſuch as are neceſſary for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3287:15"/>time. <hi>This day, &amp;c. bread.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>1</label> From the firſt branch drawn from the coherence with the former petitions, we obſerve, that</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>1</label> Such as have firſt truely ſought ſpirituall bleſſings, may comfortably aske the ſupply of their outward wants.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Ezra</hi> and the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites had ſet their faces towards Sion, and bent themſelves to erect the worſhips of God at Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, they celebrate a Faſt, to ſeeke a right way for themſelves, their lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones, and all their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3287:15"/>ſubſtance, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 8.21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and all the true Iſraelites having hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled themſelves for their ſinnes, before the Lord at Jeruſalem, and ſought for grace, then they put up their requeſt for the fruits of the land, and temporall things which the enemies poſſeſſed, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 9.36, 37.</p>
                  <p>The Prophet <hi>David,</hi> a man of much faith and grace, and a great worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of God, doth often ſollicite the Lord, for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward deliverances &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and in his owne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe and the Churches,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3287:16"/>puts up this petition, <hi>That their Garners may bee full, from kinde to kinde, that their Sheep may bring forth thouſands, their Oxen ſtrong to labour, &amp;c. Pſalm.</hi> 144.13, 14. The like did <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Agur,</hi> for their parts in their times, being both beleevers, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of God, <hi>Gene.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.8. And all theſe prayed in faith, which hath reaſon for it.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe ſo runne the Promiſes: <hi>Seeke firſt the kingdome of God, and all theſe things ſhall bee added,</hi> Math. 6.33. <hi>The Eye of the Lord is on them that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3287:16"/>feare him, upon them that hope in his mercie, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their ſoule from death, and to keepe them alive in famine,</hi> Pſalm. 33.18, 19. Such may expect it.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. Becauſe the hearts of ſuch onely are ſincere in asking theſe things, that they may uſe them to right ends, the others intending them for their luſts, which are therefore denied, <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.3.</p>
                  <p>Reproofe of two ſorts.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 1. Such as wholly and alone ſeeke for earthly and outward matters, the things of this life, that they may have ſupply accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3287:17"/>to their deſires, and care for no more, nor look any higher. Theſe as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly they pray not at all for them, ſo yet if they doe, they have no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of obtaining: becauſe their hearts are not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in the deſires of them, there being no good end propoſed, but the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying of their luſts, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the Lord owne them as his people, but they are people of the world, whoſe portion is in this life, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 17.14. ſuch as whoſe God is their belly, that minde earthly things, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. though
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3287:17"/>theſe therfore may have &amp; poſſeſſe outward matters, (as oftentimes they do) yet not as the fruits of Gods ſpeciall providence, nor teſtimonies of his favour and grace, but as effects of his generall providence, wherby he feeds and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferves all creatures, both man and beaſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.6.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Such as aske in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ſeeke in the meanes, ſome ſpirituall bleſſings, as knowledge, and faith, and grace, ſo farre as may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne their owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar good, to aſſure them of heaven, and keepe them from hell, and ſo to ſecure
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3287:18"/>them from evill; but not out of any true love to the things themſelves, (their Hearts being upon the world) much leſſe the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, the advancing of his kingdome, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his will, which are the Precedents to this fourth Petition. Theſe are but ſelfe-lovers, and not true lovers of God for his owne ſake, and therefore have no promiſe of any good, temporall or ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Comfort to all ſuch as in the truth of their hearts ſeeke, deſire, and pray for the remiſſion of ſinnes, the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3287:18"/>favour of God, the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their hearts, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Gods name, the advancing of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp;c. in the firſt place with the chiefe affection, as their onely choiſe, whatſoever elſe be denied them. Theſe have the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of adoption, they may come unto God, as their Father, and expect at his hands any ſpirituall or temporall good, bread, food, apparell, life, good ſucceſſe in their lawfull endeavours, &amp;c. as things promiſed to ſuch perſons; and if they have them not, it is becauſe the Lord will
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3287:19"/>chaſten them for ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, or trie their faith, patience, and ſubmiſſion, or recompence it in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, which are all bleſſings, and done in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to them, having this aſſurance, that they ſhall want nothing that is good for them, <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 34.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Exhortation, to all that deſire a mercifull, and comfortable adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards them, in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, to labour chiefely to ſet their hearts on things ſpirituall, to ſeeke the Kingdome of God, and his grace, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3287:19"/>then thoſe things ſhall bee ſupplyed, whatſoever is expedient: But beware of deceit, of politicke ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, of an earthly mind, whom God doth anſwere according to their heart, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.5. Croſſe then the courſe and cuſtome of the world heerein, and thou ſhalt finde beſt ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>2</label> Thus of the firſt branch. The ſecond concernes the title that wee have, or the claime that wee lay to outward matters, even neceſſaries, and on what termes wee are to aske them, that is, as gifts,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3287:20"/>
                     <hi>Give us, &amp;c.</hi> Whence we learne, that</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>2</label> Life it ſelfe, and all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comforts, are to bee asked and received as the free gifts of God. So <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob. If God will bee with mee, and will give mee bread to eate, and rayment to put on, then &amp;c.</hi> Gene. 28.20. Alſo ſpeaking to <hi>Eſau</hi> his brother, <hi>Theſe are the Children which God hath graciouſly given thy ſervant;</hi> Geneſ. 33.5. <hi>David</hi> alſo asked life, and God gave it him, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 21.4. hee tooke his life as a gift; and how thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully hee acknowledged
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3287:20"/>that, and all outward bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings elſe to bee the gifts of God, and to proceed meerely from his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is abundantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, 1. <hi>Chronic.</hi> 29.12, 16.</p>
                  <p>Not to multiply teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, (the Text it ſelfe being a univerſall and perpetuall direction in ſuch caſes) it hath this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence or ground, why they are ſo to be asked.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Becauſe they are ſuch in their nature, and can bee no otherwiſe claimed of us: For even <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocency had them all that way, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 1.29.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3287:21"/>much more having forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all by ſinne, are wee to receive them as gifts repaired by the grace of Chriſt. Hee that ſpared not his Sonne, but deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him up for us all, how ſhall hee not with him alſo<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> freely give us all things? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>verſe</hi> 32. therefore are ſo to be asked and received.</p>
                  <p>Reproofe, of all ſuch as lay arrogant and falſe claimes to the outward things they poſſeſſe, as being their owne by ſome merit, deſert, or ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie they have over them, without any rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3287:21"/>unto God at all in their thoughts or ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: Such was that lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Tyrian, who boaſted, how by his great wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and underſtanding hee had gotten him riches and treaſures.<note place="margin">Ezek. 28.4.</note> And that Aegyptian Dragon, My river is mine,<note place="margin">Ezek. 29.3.</note> and I have made it for my ſelfe. And ſuch are they that attribute all to Fortune, chance, or their owne induſtrie, or at the beſt, to ſome ſecondary cauſe or other.</p>
                  <p>Theſe perſons, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly they aske nothing at the hands of God by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3287:22"/>prayer, ſo ſeldome or never doe they returne thankes unto him for any thing they enjoy, either health, life, or any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort elſe: but ſacrifice to their Nett, and burne In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to their Dragge, as the Prophet peakes, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.16. The Lord is not at all acknowledged of them, unleſſe when they are croſſed or hindred in their expectations, then will they bee readie to murmure and exclaime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the providence of God, as if ſome great wrong were done unto them, and even to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3287:22"/>which whence comes it, but from their pride, that eſteemed them ſelves the ſole owners, and worthy of all things? To omit others taxable herein.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Exhortation to all the people of God. 1. To conſider, and conceive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right of whom they hold all their ſubſtance, and whatſoever they enjoy, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Soveraigne Lord of all, of whom they have their beings, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. 2. To aske theſe things at his hands, as gifts of his bountie, not merited, but freely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3287:23"/>in Chriſt, leaving the manner and meaſure of the diſpenſation to his owne pleaſure, who is the giver of them. 3. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne thankes unto him for whatſoever wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, and to acknowledge his goodneſſe, bee it more or leſſe. So did <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſo did <hi>David,</hi> and ſo will all that are faithfull. Thus of the ſecond branch.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>3</label> The third concernes the quantitie or meaſure of outward things, that are to bee asked at the hands of God, in prayer, and that is daily bread, neceſſaries for the preſent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3287:23"/>time: Whence wee are taught, that</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>3</label> Superfluities are not to bee asked in prayer, but that which is neceſſarie for the preſent uſe. If the Lord will give mee bread to eate, and rayment to put on, hee ſhall bee my God, ſaith <hi>Iacob, Geneſ.</hi> 28.20. Bread and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not delicates,<note place="margin">Vide Pet. Martyr in locum.</note> nor robes: uſefull matters, not unneceſſary hoards. Give mee neither povertie nor riches, (ſaith <hi>Agur</hi>) but ſeed mee with food con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for mee, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.8. and when we have food and rayment, let us
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3287:24"/>be therewith content, as the holy Apoſtle exhorts, 1. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 6.8. ſetting it in oppoſition to the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of riches, and great abundance after mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. So here our Lord di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth us to pray for dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread, or food for the day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Becauſe ſuperfluities are not promiſed, (though they are ſometime diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) but that which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to ſupport us in livelihood, and fitneſſe for our ſeverall imploiments, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 34.10. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.5. I will not faile thee, nor forſake thee.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:3287:24"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. Becauſe they are not ſafe, but full of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſnares to their poſſeſſors, 1. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 6.9. eſpecially when they are greedily deſired; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth <hi>Agur</hi> deſire and pray rather to be without them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.8. giving a reaſon for his requeſt in the verſe enſuing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Reproove, 1. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate deſires of ſuch as are not at all contented with that competencie in outward things, that the <hi>Lord</hi> hath allotted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but they luſt after great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, affluence, and ſtore, whatſoever they ſee any
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3287:25"/>other to poſſeſſe, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they conceive may bee poſſeſſed to advance themſelves and theirs to all generations. Theſe perſons are either very confident of their power to uſe ſuch things as they ought, which is a deceit too common: or elſe they regard not how they uſe them, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe of too many. Howſoever, it is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the rules of God, and to his appoynment, that will have his people con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with his allowance, and ſuch as are ſenſible of their owne good, ſubmit
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3287:25"/>unto it; they that doe not, runne into thoſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſnares, mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9. which drowne them in perdition and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in the end.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The errour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of them that under the name of daily bread, and things neceſſary, will comprehend all ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, as they conceive to bee good for them or theirs; ſuch as are health, life, libertie, peace food, rayment, good ſucceſſe in ſuch or ſuch a buſineſſe, deſigne, or purpoſe; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, charging their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3287:26"/>with as certaine a beliefe of obtaining thoſe particulars, as of remiſſion of ſinnes, the grace of God, and ſalvation it ſelfe; and thereupon condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and judging ſuch for unbeleevers in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, as obtaine not by prayer all, or any of thoſe particulars ſo conceived to be good, expedient, or neceſſary for them. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which errour, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is need) I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to lay before you ſome Arguments, and grounds out of the Word of God, as well to rectifie the Judgements of thoſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3287:26"/>that erre, as to comfort ſuch as are unworthily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected; but not to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, or ſide in a quarrell, much leſſe to reproach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mans perſon, which is far from me.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="argument">
                     <head>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 1.</head>
                     <p>Thus then I reaſon:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thoſe promiſes that have implied Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in them, cannot abſolutely bee relyed upon, or expected; for our faith is grounded on the promiſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But the promiſes of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things (although
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3287:27"/>neceſſary) are ſuch.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therefore they are not abſolutely to be rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon, or expected.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This appeares in two Caſes.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Of Chaſtiſement, when the Lord will viſit any of his people for their ſinnes; for then doth hee ſtrip them of their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comforts in part, and ſometimes wholly unto death: The former ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in all the correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the faithfull; the latter, in that example of the Jewes, <hi>Lament.</hi> 4.4.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3287:27"/>where the parents &amp; chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren both dyed through extreame famine. Yet are they not charged to want faith for this, ſo much, as but humiliation &amp; repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: and who wil beare any correction at all at the hand of God, if by his Faith hee may preſently remoove it from him? And how can that bee a ſigne of unbeliefe, that doth moſt accompany be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, and is a ſpeciall teſtimony of Gods love? <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.9.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Of Probation and Triall, when God will prove and try the patience
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3287:28"/>and obedience of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: For in that caſe, they that have beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with moſt faith and grace, have been brought to the greateſt exigents, and wants, as in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.37. they were deſtitute, afflicted, and tormented, &amp;c. 2. <hi>Corin.</hi> 11.27. <hi>Paul</hi> was pinched with hunger and thirſt, with cold and nakedneſſe; and <hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>Lazarus</hi> was in extreame povertie and dyed: yet theſe were full of faith, and of the ſpirit of God. [To which that of <hi>Iob</hi> may bee added.] Now who would endure theſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3287:28"/>trialls and diſtreſſes, if by faith and prayer hee may remove them? Or with what Warrant can they abſolutely pray againſt them, ſeeing they have no promiſe that they ſhall be ſpared? or how can Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience have her perfect worke without them? or Faith her crowne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward promiſed on that Condition? Therefore the promiſes of outward things have Conditions implyed to the people of God, and are not abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Explication.</hi> When I ſay that the promiſes of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3287:29"/>temporall things have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed conditions in them; I doe not deny that there are any conditions ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed concerning thoſe things: for it is plaine that there are, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. the whole Chapter being full of the Conditionalls, <hi>If.</hi> So <hi>Deuter.</hi> 28.1, 15. and <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.19. <hi>If yee conſent and obey, yee ſhall eate of the good of the land, &amp;c.</hi> But that ſuch promiſes as run generally, and ſeeme to be abſolute, without limitation or reſervation, (of which there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, 1. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 4.8.) have yet in regard of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3287:29"/>perſons and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, certaine conditions implyed, and reſervations to the will and pleaſure of God, in regard of corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or triall, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all his people are to ſubmit and ſubject their wills and deſires, which is their obedience, wherein by a ſecret act of recum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bencie they reſt upon the goodneſſe of God,<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> Returne of Prayers, <hi>pag.</hi> 51. <hi>&amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
                        </note> and his gracious promiſes &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, that all ſhall bee for the beſt, howſoever they have not every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular benefit they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and thinke expedient for them or theirs. And
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3287:30"/>this is that which I meane by conditions implyed.</p>
                     <p>Whereas then the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarie</hi> inſulteth in his great victorie gotten our of the word <hi>[Implyed]</hi> as arguing, that in no place conditions are expreſſed: it is very vaine, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition being directed unto Gods adminiſtration in particular, to his ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſervants, according to his will, which in that regard is ſecret to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and not revealed but by experience: for who knowes which of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, (even of the moſt faithfull) the Lord may
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3287:30"/>trie, with the want of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, <hi>Iob, Lazarus, &amp;c.</hi> notwithſtanding the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of temporall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in the generall: which ſhewes that God hath not confined him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to one onely way in dealing with his people, concerning thoſe things, but reſerved caſes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as of correction or tryall, which to ſeeke to croſſe, by an abſolute and peremptory kind of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for outward things, what is it elſe, but a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of God, a beating off (as farre as in us lyes) of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3287:31"/>his moſt uſuall and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table dealing with his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and ſo an unſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſacrifice unto him. In that reſpect therfore they have conditions implyed, as I ſay, Otherwiſe, I need not (as hee thinkes) runne to the word <hi>[Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed]</hi> for ſhelter, ſeeing there are conditions plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed, <hi>Levitic.</hi> 26. as before. And heerein I wiſh the Reader to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the fooliſh reaſoning of the <hi>Temporarie,</hi> who to diſproove conditions implyed, granteth condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions expreſſed, yet inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the contrary: For
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3287:31"/>theſe are his wordes: <q>You know and muſt needs confeſſe, that the Lord made abſolutely to his people <hi>Iſrael</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. In which promiſes there is no promiſes there is no condition implyed. It is true indeed, thoſe promiſes were made upon condition of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, &amp;c. but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition lies on their part; Gods part is abſolute, &amp;c. <bibl>
                              <hi>pag.</hi> 32.33.</bibl>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>I ſuppoſe theſe words need no other confutation than themſelves. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, were abſolute on
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3287:32"/>Gods part, the condition lyeth on their parts, <hi>If thou obey;</hi> as if the Lord had made a covenant with himſelfe, and not with men: and as if there bee conditions put in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to bee performed, the ſame were not condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall upon the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance to bee made good or not. Elſe there are no conditionall promiſes at all, but all muſt bee abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, &amp; abſolutely perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; and doubtles what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Lord hath ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely promiſed, ſhall bee abſolutely perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. His long Diſcourſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3287:32"/>then of the ſinnes and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,<note place="margin">For in that they loſt te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough their diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, it ſhewes the promiſe to be condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall.</note> is but againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, which I note the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe of his inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and reproachful taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings in that place againſt me, and my preaching, as if it were Poperie, and what not?</p>
                     <p>To my Inſtances, hee pretendeth, Firſt, that I have miſtaken their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in ſpeaking onely of Faith, whereas they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude repentance alſo, and love. Whereunto I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that in their ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous practiſe in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3287:33"/>the whole burthen was put upon Faith and beleeving generally:<note place="margin">Such was the generall complaint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o mee.</note> But this man ſteps in to refine the matter, and joynes many other things as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, which yeelds him much matter of diſcourſe, and ſo of evaſion in a miſt of many words. All which was framed ſince the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, of purpoſe (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) to hide the ſhame of their opinion: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee printeth that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my arguments, which ſhould ſtand after them.</p>
                     <p>To the ſecond inſtance hee anſweres, that thoſe things, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:3287:33"/>and the Martyrs ſuffered were bleſſings, becauſe perſecution is a bleſſing not to bee prayed againſt, &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 23.36, 67. To which I briefly reply, that perſecution in it ſelfe, and it's owne nature conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is no bleſſing, but a miſchiefe rather and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, an evill to be prayed againſt; and the contrary much to bee deſired, as plainly appeares by <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. wholly, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 122.6. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Actes</hi> 8.3, 4. compared with Chap. 9.31. Therefore is the <hi>Temporarie</hi> pitifully out, and takes<note n="*" place="margin">The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct for the ſubject.</note> one thing for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3287:34"/>another; as becauſe the perſecuted are bleſſed, &amp; that it is a bleſſed thing to ſuffer perſecution for the name of Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore perſecution it ſelfe were a bleſſing. As if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch as are ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, reviled, tortured, racked and tormented for the ſake of Chriſt, are bleſſed: therefore ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, revilings, racks, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and torments, are bleſſed things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; which if they be, then are they not only not to be prayed againſt, but to be prayed for, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. Thereupon is hee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3287:34"/>miſtaken in the Martyrs,<note place="margin">For they were offered delivernace, if they would have forſaken the truth.</note> that refuſed not delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, becauſe perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a bleſſing (as hee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes) but becauſe the Conditions were not ſuch as they could conſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, elſe had they perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves. Howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to the poynt. Seeing perſecution brings the want of outward things, and that be a ſtate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the Lord doth often call his people: to pray abſolutely againſt all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward wants, and for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward benefits, putting the fault upon impenitency or infidelitie, if wee have
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3287:35"/>them not, how weake a practiſe is it? for it is the ſame in this, as in other ſtates of affliction, all are bleſſed to the faithfull, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.12. neither hath hee any reaſon to ſingle out this from other caſes, but that hee would make matters come in to his owne way, without any ground of Scripture at all. Elſe hee would have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed ſome anſwer to the inſtance of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> [and the Story of <hi>Iob</hi>] which are againſt him in his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion directly, therefore he ſlides by them. As for the buffettings of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>Paul</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.7.</note>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3287:35"/>by Sathan, wherein his prayer in the particular was not granted,<note n="*" place="margin">In private conference.</note> hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered likewiſe, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had no Warrant to pray againſt thoſe temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,<note place="margin">A crazy paſſage ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes, &amp; againſt the ſixt Petition of the Lords Prayer.</note> being nothing elſe but Originall ſinne, which if hee had been delivered from, then he ſhould have had no need of Chriſt. It is a marveilous thing, that any man ſhould dote upon ſuch opinions, or others admire him for them. But to proceed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="argument">
                     <head>The ſecond Argument.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment </seg>2</label>
                        <hi>Such things as are ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily denied the beſt</hi>
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:3287:36"/>
                        <hi>and most faithfull ſervants of God, and accompany not their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition here, cannot be abſolutely prayed for, or expected, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil that procure them; for that were to croſſe his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But theſe matters are ſo, as is rehearſed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This appeares by two Teſtimonies.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Of Saint <hi>Iames, chap.</hi>
                           <pb n="49" facs="tcp:3287:36"/>2.5. <hi>God hath choſen the poore in this world to bee rich in faith, and heires of his Kingdome:</hi> Rich in faith, and yet outwardly poore; the abundance of faith then helpes not their povertie.</item>
                        <item>2. Of our Savior, <hi>Math.</hi> 25.35. <hi>I was hungry, and yee fed mee not; thirstie, and yee gave mee no drink; naked, and yee clothed mee not, &amp;c.</hi> Whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, that ſome of the members of Chriſt ſhall bee poore and diſtreſſed, wanting neceſſaries, in all times, to the end of the world: neither are theſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3287:37"/>taxed for want of faith at all, nor yet doth the Lord faile of any of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to his ſervants, much leſſe by a continual courſe, therefore are they deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp;c.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Explication.</hi> When I ſay that outward things are ordinarily denied to the ſervants of God, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſuch an adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in all ages and times towards ſome, and that not a few of them, ſo that it is no extraordinary mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor limitted to ſome times and ages onely, and this the inſtances prove. For when S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3287:37"/>
                        <hi>God hath choſen, &amp;c.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Non quod omnes, ſed quod plures pauperes, quam divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes hujuſmun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di elegerit Deus-Paraus in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> Hee meaneth, that in his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall counſell hee made choice of ſuch more than of others, not for their poverties ſake, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his pleaſure, not utterly excluding others, but for the moſt part, ſhewing, and manifeſting his Grace towards theſe in every age, whom hee calleth Poore, not becauſe they have not affluence and abundance, but (as the Originall word im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth) ſcarce things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>ſignif men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus,</hi> and more than <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>pauper.</hi>
                        </note> without help and ſupply from others, which outs off the anſwer of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3287:38"/>
                        <hi>Temporarie,</hi> holding thoſe poore to be ſuch as have all things convenient,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, &amp;c. Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanis Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, act. <hi>2.</hi> ſcen. <hi>5.</hi>
                        </note> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Riches and Braverie excepted (unleſſe hee will grant a contradiction in his anſwer; which is no ſtrange matter with him) and this is by an ordinary diſpenſation and courſe in all times and ages; whence it is, that I ſay, that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things accompanie not their condition here; that is, neceſſarilie, but that they may often want them.</p>
                     <p>And this may ſerve alſo to confirme the ſecond in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, out of <hi>Math.</hi> 25.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3287:38"/>For if ſome of the moſt faithful members of <hi>Chriſt</hi> want not things neceſſary in every age, how ſhall that be the triall of all the reſt that did not relieve them,<note place="margin">His myſtical interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the place, doth not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw this Collection from the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall ſenſe, which all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> or the contrary in them that did, ſeeing our Lord ſets it downe, and proclames it for a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Triall at that great day? Whereas therefore the <hi>Temporarie</hi> demands, if this be granted, that many of the Saints ſhall want neceſſaries, what will follow? I anſwer, this will follow, That Temporall neceſſaries do not neceſſarily accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3287:39"/>the ſtate of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in this life, neither is it through want of faith or repentance that many of them have them not (as hee affirmes) but they may abound in faith and grace, and excell them that have them, (CHRIST JESVS putting himſelfe in their perſons, and in that verie condition:) and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, that the promiſes of Temporall things, are not ſo abſolute without ſome conditions implyed, elſe they ſhould abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be performed to all the faithfull, the Lord being moſt true in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3287:39"/>of all his promiſes. And that then the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full themſelves are not in that peremptorie manner to require them in Praier, and to expect them ſo, as that either the Lord muſt be unjuſt, if they be not granted, or they wanting in faith and grace that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them not, which is the point in controverſie; and then his opinion is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie unſound, and his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe audacious and unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable, on the termes hee maintaines it. How fearefull then is that Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of his,<note place="margin">I uſe his owne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. <hi>page<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> 22.</note> that if any ſay they have Repentance,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3287:40"/>Faith, and Love, and miſſe of the very thing faithed in Praier: they make God a deceiver, becauſe hee never gives the one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="argument">
                     <head>The third Argument.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment </seg>3</label> 
                        <hi>That which did never put any certaine dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene one and another in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, is not the abſolute condition of thoſe things, for that cannot ſtand.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But Faith and Grace
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3287:40"/>did never put any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween one and another in outward things.</hi> Ergo, <hi>is not the abſolute condition of thoſe things, nor an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed unto them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This appeares by two places.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, Eccleſ. 9.2. <hi>All things come alike unto all, and there is one event, to him that feareth</hi> GOD, <hi>and to him that feareth him not, &amp;c. And no man knews love or hatred by all that is
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3287:41"/>before him,</hi> ver. 1. Which would not be ſo, if there were any certaine better<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the outward eſtate by Faith and Grace.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.45. <hi>Your heavenly Father ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his Sun to riſe on the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, &amp; on the good; and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Raine on the Iust and on the Vnjust.</hi> So that the verie ſame diſpenſation in outward things, belongs to one as to another, and there is no difference; Which providence doth interpret the promiſes concerning theſe things.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Explication.</hi> When I ſay that Faith and Grace
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3287:41"/>doe put no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene one and another in outward things, my meaning is (according to my words) no externall difference,<note place="margin">The inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged in a Letter to him.</note> that a believer ſhall certainly better his outward eſtate by his Faith, and an unbeliever infallibly hurt his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſtate and condition by his unbeliefe, ſo that one may be knowne from another, by their thriving or not thriving in the world, that the Children, Corne, Cattle, Ground, and Poſſeſſions of the one, ſhall be ever more proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than the other, which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3287:42"/>was my Illuſtration in my Sermon. For this is ſo contrarie to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and all experience, that it is a very ſhamefull thing to affirme it. Yet, if outward things were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily annexed to faith,<note place="margin">In regard of their fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> it muſt be ſo, and ſuch blamed for unbeliefe with whom it is otherwiſe, which were to condemne the generation of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</p>
                     <p>Whereas then the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarie</hi> produceth divers promiſes out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, containing bleſſings belonging to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3287:42"/>and their ſeed; and on the contrary, many threatnings to the wicked in that kind: hee ſhould have done well withall, to have anſwered thoſe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and reſolved thoſe Caſes, that troubled <hi>Iob</hi> and his friends, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Ieremie,</hi> about theſe matters; the former uttering his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint thus: <hi>Wherefore doe the wicked live, become old, and are mightie in power? Their ſeed is eſtabliſhed in their ſight, and their off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring before their eyes. Their houſes are ſafe from feare, neither is the rod
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3287:43"/>of God upon them, &amp;c.</hi> Job 21.7, 8. The other thus confeſſing: <hi>My feet were almoſt gone, my ſteps had welnigh ſlipt: for I was envious at the fooliſh, when I ſaw the proſperitie of the wicked. There are no bands in their death, but their ſtrength is firme, they are not in trouble as other men, neither are they plagued like other men. All the day long have I beene plagued and chastened every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 73.3, 4. &amp;c. <hi>Ieremy</hi> in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner expoſtulating with the Almighty: <hi>Wherefore doth the way of the wicked pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper?
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3287:43"/>Wherefore are all they happy that deale very trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly? Thou haſt planted them, they have taken root, they grow, they beare fruit,</hi> Jerem. 12.1.2. He ſhould have reſolved theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſhewed how this could ſtand with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of outward bleſſings to the faithfull, and the contrarie to the wicked, and then hee had done ſomething: But this, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through ignorance hee paſſeth over, or elſe, purpoſely, becauſe it made againſt him, hee paſſeth by in ſilence. Neither could hee ſay any thing to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3287:44"/>
                        <hi>Iob</hi> or <hi>David,</hi> if hee had beene with them (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne way) in thoſe caſes, but that there was a Plague in their hearts, and they wanted Repentance, Faith, or Love, elſe it had beene otherwiſe with them, and ſo hee might have gone amongſt <hi>Iob's</hi> miſerable comforters, of whom hee complaines, <hi>Iob</hi> 16.2.</p>
                     <p>But it is evident out of thoſe teſtimonies, and the like adminiſtration in all times, that faith and grace doth not make or diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any certain difference betweene one and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3287:44"/>in outward things to bee knowne by, but that the moſt faithfull may be in deepe adverſities, while the wicked proſper and flouriſh. Concerning then thoſe temporall promiſes under the Law, upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of obedience, it is evident that they were part of the Pedagogie of the Jewes, to traine them on, and allure them to be obedient to the Law of God, as alſo to lead them to the conſideration of better things, as the milke and honey, the corne, the wine and oyle of the land of Canaan alſo were.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3287:45"/>Whereas now under the Goſpell wee have a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Covenant,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> eſtabliſhed upon better promiſes, the ſpirituall bleſſings of the kingdome of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Hebr. 8.6.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, peace of conſcience, the Holy Spirit, with the graces thereof, and the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting reſt to come. And for thoſe temporall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, they may bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendices to the Covenant, in as much as Chriſt is made Heyre of all things,<note place="margin">So <hi>Calvin</hi> on Heb. 1.2.</note> and ſo doe moſt properly belong unto the faithfull: yet ſeeing none are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly obedient, and the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3287:45"/>Lord doth direct and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all to the everlaſting good of his people, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither under the Law heretofore, nor now under the Goſpell were thoſe temporall benefites neceſſarily conferrd upon the juſt, but their faith and patience were exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed and tryed with the want of them, more or leſſe, according as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lord to ſingle out any of his ſervants, (as he hath done many) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; and that without either breach of promiſe in God, or want of faith and grace in his ſervants
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3287:46"/>and people: ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the bleſſing doe belong truly to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and their ſeed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures, yet the outward benefits themſelves in particular, are not ever ſo beſtowed upon the beleevers, as that thereby they may certainly be knowne and diſtinguiſhed from others, the Lord reſerving that in his owne power, to deale according to his holy pleaſure and will with his owne, having alwayes in ſtore better things for them, than he doth at any time deny them.</p>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:3287:46"/>
                     <p>My Inſtances produced for the proofe of what I affirme, the <hi>Temporary</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to put by with his Interpretations, as of <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 9.2. <hi>All things come alike to all, &amp;c.</hi> which hee would have to bee the judgement of the world, onely recited by <hi>Salomon,</hi> but not approved of, that the world doth ſo thinke and ſpeake, that all things come alike, and there is one event; but it is not ſo indeed, this being an evill under the Sunne, (which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaw) that men thinke, and ſpeake ſo, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that a paralell unto
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3287:47"/>it, in <hi>Malac.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Your words have beene ſtout a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee, in that yee ſay, it is in vaine to ſerve God, &amp;c.</hi> Wherein 1. he walks alone, having no Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to concurre with him, or aſſiſt him in that ſenſe (that hee knew) as hee confeſſed in a private Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Hee runnes directly againſt <hi>Salomons</hi> intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">See Eccleſ. 2.14, 15.</note> and overturnes the coherence with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer words, and the drift of the place, which is to ſhew, that the perſons and workes of good and bad, are ſo under the power
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3287:47"/>and providence of God, and ordered by him, that no man was certaine to better his outward eſtate by his obedience, &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, but that the ſame event in outward things might befall him, that befell the wicked and ungodly, which is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill under the Sunne, that is, one of thoſe grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that in this world de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed any perfect happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the juſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in as much as all their obedience could not ſecure them from the common evill events of the ungodly, but that all
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3287:48"/>things came alike to all, and no certaine difference did outwardly appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, in life, or in death. Which is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by that pertinent place to this purpoſe, <hi>chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 8.14. <hi>There be just men to whom it happeneth according to the work of the wicked, and there be wicked men to whom it happeneth according the worke of the righteous.</hi> A wicked man may be viſited with Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Peſtilence, or the Sword, ſo may the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: an ungodly perſon may be croſſed and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in his perſon, off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3287:48"/>eſtate, and name, ſo may the moſt godly and faithfull:<note place="margin">See <hi>Weemes</hi> Chriſtian Synagogue. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. fully of this point.</note> The holy Scriptures are full of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples; as in <hi>Iob, David, Hezekiah,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for as died <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ahab,</hi> ſo died <hi>Ionathan</hi> and good <hi>Ioſiah.</hi> As for that place then in <hi>Malachie,</hi> it containes nothing but the evill conſequence and uſe that ſome men made of the proſpering of the wicked, and the afflictions of the juſt. As if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were in vaine to ſerve God, and there were no profit at all in it, either here, or hereafter: which
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3287:49"/>very Temptation aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the heart of <hi>David,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Or of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaph</hi> as ſome thinke.</note> as hee confeſſeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.13. <hi>Verely I have cleanſed my heart in vaine, &amp;c.</hi> But hee was ſatisfied and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to the contrary out, of the word of God. All which doe plainly prove the point in hand, that outward bleſſings or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits are not neceſſarily and infallibly annexed to faith, and to the faithfull, for the fruition of them; and ſo the contrary to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers (as the <hi>Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> would have it) to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference the one from the other.</p>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:3287:49"/>
                     <p>And concerning that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther teſtimony taken from <hi>Math.</hi> 5.45. Hee labours to avoid it, by ſhewing, that the outward benefits the faithfull enjoy, they have by promiſe through Chriſt, but the others not ſo; whereas that is no part of the Queſtion, how, or by what claime either of them have theſe things, but that they have them: neither of the internall difference that faith and grace makes between one and another, which no man doubteth of, but the externall difference in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, whether that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3287:50"/>be certaine, as thereby to difference the good from the bad, which is the point controverted, and this not onely the former inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces diſprove, but this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie, confirmed by common and daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; in that the evill, and the good, the juſt, and the unjuſt are equally par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the benefit of Sun and Raine,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Muſcul:</hi> in locum. Quare Deus non diſcrimines inter bones &amp; males.</note> with other generall effects of Gods gracious providence and goodneſſe, as our Saviour there reaſoneth; which I ſay, therefore doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to all, that is, that by a generall diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3287:50"/>all are partakers of them.</p>
                     <p>And thus I conclude, (not to trace him further in his wandrings) that the promiſes of outward things are not ſo abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made unto the faithfull, as that by the fruition of them, they are certainly differenced from others: and that the Lord muſt bee unjuſt, if hee deny theſe things unto his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, upon their Praiers, or they wanting in faith, or ſome neceſſary grace in themſelves, which is the maine opinion of the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarie.</hi> So to proceed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="argument">
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:3287:51"/>
                     <head>The fourth Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment </seg>4</label> 
                        <hi>That which the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus and his Apoſtles did pray for, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst conditionally, is ſo to be done of us: for wee are bid to follow their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and to try our Spirits and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by theirs, and not theirs by ours.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But our Lord and his Apostles did ſo.</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go.</p>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:3287:51"/>
                     <p>This is proved by two places.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.42. <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if thou be willing, let this Cup paſſe from mee, yet not my will, but thine be done.</hi> Here is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation of an outward evill, not abſolutely, but with ſubmiſſion to the will of God.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Making request, if by any meanes, I might have a proſperous journey, by the will of God to come unto you.</hi> Here is an outward benefit; yea, ſomewhat more (a ſervice to the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3287:52"/>Church) deſired with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Gods will. And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames</hi> layes downe a rule for all to follow in ſuch caſes. Yee ought to ſay, <hi>If God will. Iam.</hi> 4.15. What is it then to teach that wee ought not to ſay, <hi>If the Lord will,</hi> but directly to croſſe the word of God?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Explication.</hi> The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is grounded upon the examples of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, in a morall dutie, that concernes all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in all times to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe; that is, prayer unto God, and ſubmiſſion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3287:52"/>to his will: In which caſes wee have Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements given us in the Word, to follow their ſteps, and to doe as wee have them for examples. <hi>For I have given you an example, that yee ſhould doe, as I have done to you,</hi> John 13.15. <hi>Leaving us an example, that we ſhould follow his ſtepps,</hi> 1. Pet. 2.21. <hi>Bee yee Followers of mee, as I alſo am of Chriſt,</hi> 1. Corin. 11.1. <hi>To make our ſelves an enſample to you to follow us,</hi> 2. Theſſ. 3.9. <hi>Thoſe things which yee have both learned, and received, and heard, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3287:53"/>ſeene in mee, doe.</hi> Phil. 4.9. Wherein Examples in morall duties, are propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for imitation, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe perfect pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of him, who did no ſin, neither was guile found in his mouth, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22.<note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of God.</note> This being the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie that I have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, That in matters pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to his Office of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatorſhip, as to bee a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſinne, to make atonement, to preſent our prayers unto God: or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar and proper to his divine nature and power, as to walke upon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to raiſe from the dead,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3287:53"/>&amp;c. Wee neither are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,<note place="margin">See Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> nor yet is it in our power to imitate his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but in matters of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall obedience;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Vide Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium in</hi> 1. <hi>Petri.</hi> cap. 2. ver. 21.</note> as in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Humility, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Love, Submiſſion to the will of his Father, his example and patterne is propoſed, and recorded for our imitation and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe; and of this nature is the point in queſtion. Which I therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not indefinitely, as to ſay, that That which our Saviour Chriſt did in generall (without limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) is to be done of us: But what hee did in this
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:3287:54"/>matter of Praier being a Morall duty, and ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Apoſtles. Which to ſay, is a doctrine fit to bee ſpewed out of the Church (as the <hi>Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> doth in his anſwer) how beaſtly and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous is it? And for the ground of his ſpeech, that we are to live by rules and precepts, and not by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, that being a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> it is even as vaine.<note place="margin">Exemphim Christi, est praxis theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiae, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </note> For are wee not commanded to follow the examples of Chriſt, in thoſe things, as before hath been ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Which generall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3287:54"/>comprehends all particulars, of that nature, that they need not bee mentioned, as the <hi>Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie</hi> fooliſhly requireth; neither is this any Pillar, eſpecially a chiefe Pillar of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (as hee ſpeaketh) to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate our Saviour Chriſt, and the holy Apoſtles in Morall duties, and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of obedience, for then they would have better Pillars to ſupport them, than we know they have any. It is well ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for them, but ſimply for himſelfe, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth all the Churches
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3287:55"/>of Chriſt, as no Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, for not imitating thoſe firſt patternes of the Apoſtles, and their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in thoſe times (as hee elſewhere alleageth.) Therefore herein I teach no Will-worſhip, nor I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous action, nor any thing tending that way: but what is warranted by Scripture, and backt with reaſon.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Keck: de lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis commu.</hi> pag. 281. See <hi>Perkins</hi> in Math. 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 328.</note> 
                        <hi>Exempla enim ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ſunt aliud, quàm gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis doctrinae, &amp; regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum univerſalium ſpecialia ſymbola.</hi> Our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confuteth the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, and defendeth his Diſciples partly by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:3287:55"/>
                        <hi>Mathew</hi> 12.3. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> proveth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth the greateſt Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our faith, by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.22, 23. The holy Scriptures of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes recommend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, the examples of the Patriarcks, the Prophets, the Martyrs, as patternes for our imitation, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. &amp;c. Therefore how rude is this man to reject the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and the Apoſtles, with ſuch foule language as hee doth? But hee hath ſomewhat to ſay againſt the Proofes.</p>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:3287:56"/>
                     <p n="1">1. That Prayer of our Saviour (he ſaith) was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from him; the horribleneſſe of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for mans ſinne retaining for a time, the whole humane mind, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till his Divinitie raiſed him up againe; after which hee ſpake after another manner, as <hi>Matthew</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, alledging the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of a nameleſſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, that it was <hi>Nequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam juſta precatio.</hi> Chriſt knowing full well that hee muſt die, &amp;c. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I anſwer, that is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that our Lord did never any finfull action,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3287:56"/>neither was hee ſubject with <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſpeake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedly with his lips through diſtemper:<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.33.</note> Nor was his Humanitie ever tainted or overcome with any ſinfull perturbations,<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthon:</hi> De Paſsione Christs per Pezelium. <hi>pag. 282.</hi>
                        </note> or impotent Paſſions, as either to deſire, or to utter things unlawfull or evill, that none might imitate: therefore, howſoever his agonie was very great,<note place="margin">Chriſti tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidationes non fuerunt ſimiles noſtris. <hi>ibidem.</hi>
                        </note> and the Humanity did that which was proper unto it, ſeeke the diverting of an evill, if it might be, yet withall, at the ſame inſtant hee doth adviſedly and holily ſubmit himſelfe to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3287:57"/>his Fathers will therein, without any reluctancie at all, being one entire acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How ſuſpitiouſly and dangerouſly then doth the <hi>Temporarie</hi> handle this Praier, as if it were ſome unadviſed ſpeech, and fall of the Humanitie, out of which the Divinitie reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him againe. For the defence wherof he would make one Evangeliſt to contradict another, and citeth a nameleſſe Author, ſaying, that it was <hi>Nequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam justa precatio</hi> (a ſpeech that had need be warily underſtood) and all this to explode this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample<note place="margin">Or rather to be abhorred</note>
                        <pb n="91" facs="tcp:3287:57"/>from imitiation, and ſo to eſtabliſh his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
                     <p>But for the clearing of all this, I thinke it fit to produce the judgement of a godly learned Author on the place, ſpeaking thus:<note place="margin">It is the collection of moſt Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> 
                        <hi>Attamen ut libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur petit, unde colligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp;c.</hi> 
                        <q>Yet hee deſireth to bee freed. Whence wee gather, that it is lawfull for us to deprecate thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, that are approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: For if it be natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to grieve for them, then are not they to be condemned that deſire
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:3287:58"/>to be freed from them. But herein, the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or correction that Chriſt doth uſe is diligently to bee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, when hee addeth, <hi>Yet not my will, but thine be done:</hi> In which ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hee asketh that, which hee teacheth us to aske, <hi>Thy will be done in earth, as it is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> This therefore may be a rule to us of all our Praiers, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things of this life, wherein it is not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to us what the Lord would have to be done. And ſuch are too
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:3287:58"/>bold and confident, as will undertake to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe unto him, on whoſe ſole pleaſure we depend, and all ours. This being the reaſon why the Praiers of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie are not heard, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are bold, not ſo properly to pray, as with a kind of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to command, and to preſcribe unto God what they will have to bee done for them. <bibl>
                              <hi>Gaulther</hi> in <hi>Luke</hi> 22.42.</bibl>
                        </q> Which one teſtimonie might be ſufficient to end the Controverſie, were the Adverſarie reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:3287:59"/>but hee hath more to ſay.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That of <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.10. doth ſhew the deſire S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> had to come to them, but hee had no promiſe of God, that hee ſhould come to them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it's no marvell that hee puts in an [<hi>If,</hi>] as any one muſt doe, when hee asketh what God hath not promiſed, &amp;c. To which I anſwer. 1. That here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I cannot but marvell at the daring ſpirit of this man, that in the former Proofe, doth little better than taxe the LORD JESVS himſelfe of ſome
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3287:59"/>fall and fault in his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Praier: And here hee accuſeth the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle for praying (and that very often) for ſuch a thing as for which hee had no promiſe that hee ſhould be heard.<note place="margin">Without ceaſing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is no marvell (ſaith hee) though hee doubteth, ſeeing hee had no promiſe, &amp;c. For, whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin, and where there is no promiſe at all, there can be no faith. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe frequent praiers of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> were offred up without faith, and were ſinfull Praiers, by his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:3287:60"/>who elſwhere affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth,<note place="margin">Page 15.</note> that faith and doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting are ſo contrary, that <hi>côdem inſtanti,</hi> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand together; and that the word [<hi>If</hi>] ariſing from thence, doth ſtand betweene God and us, as a cloud. This is his arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant cenſure of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles prayers.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. I would demaund of him, or any that hold with him, whether Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had not as much ground of aſſurance, and as certaine a promiſe, for his comming to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> as the <hi>Temporarie,</hi> or any other have of any
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3287:60"/>particular Temporall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit they aske at the hands of God, for the promiſes run onely in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. It is not ſaid of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie particular perſon, that hee ſhall have this or that particular Favour, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, or Requeſt, but in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall onely, and all this S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> had. For as a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever hee had the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of thoſe Temporall benefits that were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for him; as an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hee had a ſpeciall promiſe from Chriſt of aſſiſtance in Preaching the Coſpel to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> (of which the <hi>Romanes</hi> were
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:3287:61"/>part) <hi>Act.</hi> 26.17. As an earneſt Petitioner for this particular favour, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more neceſſarie than any Temporall matter,) hee had as much, and far more promiſe of audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, than any <hi>Temporary</hi> believer hath of any Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall benefit that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives to be good for him. And yet had hee no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe for what hee asked? What promiſe then hath the <hi>Temporary</hi> for all his Temporals, whereof hee is ſo confident? But what if the Apoſtle had a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe from God, and a particular aſſurance of his
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3287:61"/>comming to the <hi>Romanes?</hi> for it is certaine that hee had a promiſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>Rome, Act.</hi> 23.11. and before that hee was aſſured of it, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.21. And when hee wrote the Epiſtle hee was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident in it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.24. Where then is the truth of the <hi>Temporarie,</hi> in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that hee prayed for that, for which hee had no promiſe.</p>
                     <p>Which practiſe elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, hee calleth bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, in two places, <hi>Page</hi> 20. &amp; 57. Doth it not rather appeare herehence, that in all our underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:3287:62"/>wee are to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon God, and to wait upon his will, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning our ſelves to his good pleaſure, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in our prayers either expreſly, or implicitly to deſire (as the Apoſtle doth) by the will of God to doe this or that worke, to have this or that bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit from him, to make our journeys proſperous, &amp;c. (as the word importeth:<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. As we ſay, A good journey.</note>) and not as the <hi>Temporary</hi> proudly teacheth, <hi>Give</hi> me this, and give me that, for I know it is good for mee? which kind of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage wiſe Parents would
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:3287:62"/>not allow in their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Doubtleſſe, it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues not a little arrogancy in this man, to quarrell ſo with the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, deſiring by the will of god to have a proſperous journey to the <hi>Romanes.</hi> May hee not as well alter the third <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and ſay not, <hi>Thy will be done,</hi> but Our wils bee done, in our prayers? for it tends unto it apace. But he goes on further yet.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 That of Saint <hi>Iames, Ye ought to ſay, If the Lord will,</hi> is intended onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe vaine boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who would perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorily
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:3287:63"/>ſay, <hi>We will goe to ſuch a Citie, &amp;c.</hi> ſeeing no man knowes that hee ſhall live a day, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerre it to prayer for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall neceſſaries is a groſſe abuſe, ſeeing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Saying,</hi> and wee of <hi>Praying.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For anſwer whereunto, I ſay, that Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeakes not, onely of ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, neither is it the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or not ſaying of thoſe words ſimply,<note place="margin">So <hi>Calvin</hi> on the place.</note> that hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth, but the reproofe of the arrogant confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and groundleſſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie of ſuch, as if their lives and actions had been
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:3287:63"/>in their owne power, and all at their owne diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, would without any acknowledgment of God, or dependance upon his providence, conſidently undertake all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, neither in heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, nor in words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing any ſubmiſſion at all to the will of God, or dependance on his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence: Againſt both which evills doth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle inveigh, teaching men as wel in their hearts to acknowledge, as by their tongues to confeſſe their relying wholly upon God, and dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:3287:64"/>on his will, in all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes &amp; purpoſes: which thing hath ſuch relation to Prayer, as that the one cannot ſtand in truth without the other, neither are they ever ſevered in practiſe; for hee that doth truely acknowledge the ſoveraigntie of God in all things, and his abſolute power over him and his actions, will alſo by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayer ſeeke his grace and favour, to diſpoſe of him in mercy for the beſt, conſidering his owne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe of any good.<note place="margin">My times are in thy hand. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.15.</note> And ſeeing the counſell and purpoſe of God is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3287:64"/>to us, concerning our lives, our eſtates, and the event of all our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; ſuch a one will with ſubmiſſion to the will of God, offer up his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts concerning out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things: as, if it may ſtand with his pleaſure to grant him this or that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, or favour: if it may tend to his glorie: if it may further our everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting good, &amp;c. and ſo ſpeake before men. Of which practiſe, what bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter patterne can wee have than that of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who not onely offered his prayers in ſuch caſes (and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3287:65"/>that more than of a ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar nature) with ſuch a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive,<note place="margin">If the Lord permit; if God will, &amp;c.</note> if, but uſed it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in his ſpeeches and writings, as appeares by <hi>Act.</hi> 18.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.10 <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.19, 24. and yet had a more ſpeciall and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular promiſe in thoſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, than any man now can ordinarily have; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath he ever till now (that I have heard) beene taxed for unbeliefe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or praying without a promiſe, much leſſe bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, <hi>proh ſcelus!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And heerein I wiſh the <hi>Temporary</hi> would take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3287:65"/>of his notable igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and raſhneſſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who in grounding his opinion for abſolute prayer, hath reference onely to the revealed will of God, excluding his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret counſell and purpoſe altogether. For although it be true, that the written Word of God doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in it a perfect diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of good and evill, to regulate our obedience: and that therein is plainly declared, what things are lawfull or unlawfull, (for the generall matter of them) to bee asked at his hands: yet for the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3287:66"/>of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, to whom, how, and in what manner thoſe things ſhall bee done, it is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, but reſerved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſecret counſell and purpoſe, to bee ordered and diſpoſed according to thoſe glorious ends that hee hath ordained and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted.<note place="margin">Dan. 4.35. Pſal. 33.11.</note> And this is that will,<note place="margin">So <hi>Tareus</hi> on the place.</note> which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth in the forenamed places, and that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames</hi> heere meaneth, when hee requires that wee ſay, <hi>If the Lord will.</hi> For S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>Paul</hi> doubted not of the revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led will of God, for the lawfulneſſe of his deſire
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:3287:66"/>to goe to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> but for the time, the comfort of his journey, and the good ſucceſſe, which were ſecrets, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he deſires favour. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth Saint <hi>Iames</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the lawfulneſſe of travelling to Cities and Townes, in mens lawfull trades, for commerce and gaine, as if it agreed not with the revealed will of God: but the purpoſe of God concerning the lives of particular perſons, and their ſeverall ſucceſſes therein, which is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to his ſecret will, which they knew not; and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:3287:67"/>therefore are to interpoſe that condition,<note place="margin">Hebr 6.3.</note> 
                        <hi>If the Lord will,</hi> or, <hi>If God permit.</hi> Which conſideration the <hi>Temporarie</hi> will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, but ſtands on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the revealed will, as if it were definite &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate to each parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, concerning perſons and matters, making great adoe about the ſufficiency of the Scriptures, and the abſoluteneſſe of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, as if the purpoſe of God concerning the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall condition of all his ſervants were there mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, or were to bee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered one way. <hi>Iob, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3287:67"/>Salomon,</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, <hi>Lazarus,</hi> (whether it bee a parable or not) were all the ſervants of God, had all the ſame generall promiſes, and yet their outward conditions were very different, which was not revealed to them in the word, but by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whereby that ſecret will of God was ſeene; and heere is the ſubmiſſion of the faithfull, when they pray that the will and purpoſe of God concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, may bee effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in mercie towards them, &amp; themſelves pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſubmit unto it, croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:3287:68"/>and denying their owne wills and deſires: ſo that if it pleaſe the Lord to trie them by wants, and by a low e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Lazarus,</hi> they are contented: if by any other croſſes &amp; great afflictions, they ſay <hi>Thy will bee done:</hi> and they challenge nothing of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, but that they bee not forſaken, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.5. Vnto this will therefore all the ſervants of God are to ſubmit themſelves, not onely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in deed, but in word, and that not in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alone, but in praying, if it ſtand with the will of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:3287:68"/>their Father, if it bee his pleaſure,<note place="margin">Which is an, <hi>If,</hi> of ſubmiſſion, not of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe.</note> if it bee good for them, if it tend to his glory, to take off ſuch a croſſe, to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tow ſuch a favour on them, which is not contrary to the revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led will, (the promiſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indefinite) but agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to it, that hath taught us in ſuch caſes ſo to pray: therefore are we not gone from praying to bare ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as the <hi>Temporary</hi> drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and ſo his taunting ſpeeches at the word <hi>(If)</hi> in prayer, as arguing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies infidelity, as a cloud that ſtands betweene God and us: as that which
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:3287:69"/>makes our prayers not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the word: as that which deprives us of many bleſſings, as that which lulls men in ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c. are no other then the froth of Imagination, and the vaniſhing vapour of errour. And his dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in all our prayers for temporall things to come unto God in this ſort, Lord, thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to aske the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing wee now deſire, and therefore wee expect it at thy hands, here is our Evidence, wee know it is good for us, &amp;c. charging the Lord with his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3287:69"/>miſe, &amp; condemning them that miſſe of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, ſo asked with unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, and a plague in their hearts, is a preſumptuous kind of praying, and an unwarrantable ground of cenſuring. And thus of the fourth Argument.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="argument">
                     <head>The fifth Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment </seg>5</label> 
                        <hi>If the Faith of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles was limited and bounded by the will of God, then all other faith is ſo: But the faith of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:3287:70"/>was confined to the will of God, and his pleaſure.</hi> Ergo.</p>
                     <p>This appeares,
<list>
                           <item>1. By <hi>Actes</hi> 19.12. where it is plaine, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had the Faith of Miracles, and healed Diſeaſes.</item>
                           <item>2. Yet. 2. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 4.20. Hee complaines that hee left <hi>Trophimus</hi> at <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> ſicke. No doubt but hee deſired his health, and prayed for it, but could not obtaine it, though it bee promiſed, that the prayer of Faith ſhall heale
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:3287:70"/>the ſicke, <hi>Iames</hi> 5.15. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſubject to Gods pleaſure and will; which ſhewes the promiſes to be conditionall.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Explication.</hi> The grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of my Argument is, that the faith of Miracles, and the gift of healing the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in thoſe times, had as certaine and as ſpeciall promiſes, as a juſtifying Faith hath for any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Temporalls; which is prooved by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and power given the Apoſtles, <hi>Mathew.</hi> 10.8. Heale the ſicke, cleanſe the Lepers, raiſe the dead, caſt out Devills,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:3287:71"/>&amp;c. and by that of <hi>Iames,</hi> the prayer of Faith ſhall ſave the ſicke, and the Lord ſhal raiſe him up, &amp;c. <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.15. which yet was ſo confined to the will of God, that al were not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or raiſed thereby,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wins</hi> returne of prayers, pag. 50.</note> for then none muſt have died at all, or if they had, muſt have beene raiſed up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Therfore notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thoſe abſolute promiſes, a ſecrer reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the will of GOD, was implyed in regard of the particulars, ſo it was limited and bounded. To which the <hi>Pemporary</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth, That both the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:3287:71"/>Faith of Myracles, and all other Faith, had no other bound but the revealed will of God, utterly deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the other, and therup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Argument. Which if it were ſo, then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer conſequence muſt needs follow, that all muſt bee healed, and all raiſed, ſeeing the promiſes runne abſolute, and generall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the letter, and are ſo to bee underſtood, according to his owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, without any other li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation intended.</p>
                     <p>Whereas then I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the example of <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phimus,</hi> whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
                        <pb n="120" facs="tcp:3287:72"/>left behind him ſicke, to prove the gift of healing not to be unlimited; uſing theſe words, no doubt, he deſired his health, and prayed for it, &amp;c. To this hee anſwereth deridingly (after his manner) <q>Who told you, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> prayed for the health of <hi>Trophimus?</hi> another may ſay no doubt, he did not pray for him, &amp;c. The ſecret things belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. I know not how it can bee rightly reſolved, unleſſe you call <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Trophimus</hi> from the dead againe.</q> Wherein I cannot but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:3287:72"/>the rudeneſſe of this mans ſpirit, and language, that before chargeth the Apoſtle with unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, and praying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any promiſe, which in two other places hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth babbling: and heere he queſtioneth his Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, making a great doubt, whether hee did ſo much as offer up a prayer for his ſicke friend to recover him. It is no marvell, if he viliſie others with his foule language, that dares thus to handle the holy Apoſtle. Would not hee himſelfe thinke it much to be ſo taxed? to be with a
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:3287:73"/>Chriſtian in ſickneſſe, to have neede of his health, yet not ſo much as to offer up a prayer unto God for him, but there to leave him? Surely it were no Chriſtian cariage, and therefore moſt unmeet to be imputed to ſo excellent a perſon for grace and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was. For my part then, I ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as I ſaid before, that there is no doubt but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> prayed for <hi>Trophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Hee that preſſeth this duty ſo much upon all Chriſtians, in his Epiſtles, that practiſed the ſame ſo much himſelfe for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:3287:73"/>ant that by name,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.16. Col. 1.9. Phil. 1 3.4. 1 Theſ. 1.2.</note> being abſent from them: that was ſo full of grace and love himſelfe: that for a beleever, a compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him in his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.4. he ſhould not offer up a prayer for him in his ſickenes, being preſent with him, ſhall ſtill be uncredible to me, and the contrary no ſecret nor uncertain collection. Now if he did pray for him, and yet he was not recovered by it, as the Text ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, then it followes, that the faith of myracles and gift of healing, and ſo all prayer for temporall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:3287:74"/>on our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are confined unto the will and pleaſure of God,<note place="margin">The a. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Tim.</hi> ſeemes to be written long after S. <hi>Paul</hi> was at Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. <hi>Ergo, Trophimus</hi> remained ſick, long.</note> in reſpect of the particulars, although the promiſes runne abſolute and generall, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have implyed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in them, which is the point in Queſtion. Whence it will alſo fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that prayers offered up for all ſuch things, are to be made with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall <hi>If,</hi> it ſtand with the will and pleaſure of GOD, expreſſed, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed and intended.</p>
                     <p>And thus have I forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied my <hi>Five Arguments,</hi>
                        <pb n="125" facs="tcp:3287:74"/>which the <hi>Temporary</hi> ſo ſcornefully oppoſeth, not tracting nor following therein his rambling diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, and wandring im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinences, which were endleſſe; much leſſe his ridiculous deſcants,<note place="margin">In his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Second part.</note> and idle inconſequences, as not becomming the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitie of the matter, and point in hand: but onely diſcovering and urging what I conceive for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to bee pertinent to the point, and agreeable to the Truth.</p>
                     <p>There were alſo a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or two added and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, neceſſary for the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:3287:75"/>removing of ſuch ſcruples and doubts as may ariſe in the mindes of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter, which I thinke fit to ſet downe and explaine.</p>
                     <p>Queſt. <hi>If any aske, how then ſhall we pray in Faith, for any outward things if it be uncertaine, whether wee ſhall have them?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer: wee beleeve that we ſhall have whatſoever is good for us (which the Lord beſt knoweth) either the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward benefit, or grace to ſupply it, as 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 12.9.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Explication.</hi> That which
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:3287:75"/>is ſaid to bee good for us, I underſtand two wayes, Poſitively, or Privative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: 1. Poſitively, when wee have the very bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits themſelves in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar that wee deſire, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> had a ſonne of his owne to be his heire, <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſon</hi> had water at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, <hi>Iudges</hi> 15.19, &amp;c. 2. Privately, when the thing wee deſire is denied us, but a better is beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon us, either corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, or ſpirituall, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was denyed <hi>Eliezer</hi> or <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> (which hee intended,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.18, 19.</note> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> though hee prayed for it)
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:3287:76"/>but had an <hi>Iſaack</hi> to bee his heire,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.28.</note> the heire of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.<note place="margin">Deut. 3.24. &amp;c.</note> 
                        <hi>Moſes</hi> was denied an entrance into the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Canaan,</hi> but was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into a heavenly. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was denyed upon his earneſt and often requeſt,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> the remooving of a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but had a better thing given; grace ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for him, and a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed uſe of the affliction. Which things were all good for them, and farre better than the things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, which they reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and prayed for; And this by the Lords diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, who knoweth beſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:3287:76"/>what is good for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and for the glory of his owne name; deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore many things in mercie, which he might grant in judgement. Now this then is certaine, that whatſoever is good for the people of God, they ſhall obtaine by prayer, according to his gracious promiſes made to them, upon which they are to ground their confidence in prayer,<note place="margin">Pſ. 34.10, 17 pſa. 84.11.</note> without any wavering or doubting at all, which is ſufficient, though they bee held in ſuſpenſe concerning the particulars, and reſigne
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:3287:77"/>themſelves therein to the will of God:<note place="margin">Quod utilo eſt agr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, magis novit madieus qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tus. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                        </note> therefore is ſuch a ſubmiſſion no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to faith in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at all, neither are their prayers in vaine, though they bee not their owne chooſers.</p>
                     <p>Object. <hi>Wee may pray abſolutely for things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, as wee may, to doe the will of God, and that his name might bee glorified by us; ſeeing ſuch things conduce thereunto.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sol.</hi> The will of God is done and his name glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, as well by our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, as by our active obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, in ſuffering quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:3287:77"/>his pleaſure and will, and hath the like reward, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.19. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.12.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Explication.</hi> I hold and beleeve, that ſuch things as neceſſarily and directly tend to the glory of God, and the ſalvation of mens ſoules, they may abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray for, as being the ſumme of all our deſires; and that therfore we may abſolutely pray for grace,<note place="margin">Iere. 31.18. Luke 11.11 Luke 17.5. Math. 6.10.</note> for faith, for repentance, for the feare of God, for his holy Spirit, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily conduce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. But for externall things with their perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall relations, wee cannot
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:3287:78"/>in that manner importune the Lord for them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee know not what way God will be glorified by us, whether by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying, or the not inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them; nor by what courſe hee will ſave our ſoules, whether by giving us theſe things, or by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of them, which is the more uſuall, nor yet yeeld us helpe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort by remooving our temptations and ſorrows, or by giving us grace and ſtrength ſufficient to beare them, and rightly to uſe them. For the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which truth, heare
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:3287:78"/>Maſter <hi>Calvin</hi> anſwering an Objection,<note place="margin">Calvin in 2. Cor. 12 9.</note> Whether Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (ſeeing he was denied his requeſt) prayed in faith or not, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of the temptation upon him: <q>I anſwere (ſaith hee) as there is a divers way of asking, ſo there are two kinds of obtaining. Wee aske thoſe things ſimply, of which wee have a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine promiſe; ſuch are th' eſtabliſhing of the kingdome of God, the hallowing of his name, remiſſion of ſinnes, and whatſoever tends to our ſalvation: but when we
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:3287:79"/>thinke the kingdome of God may or ought to be furthered by this or that way or meanes, this or that thing to be nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the hallowing of hisname, we are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten deceived. Likewiſe do we manytimes faile in things that concern our ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore thoſe former things, we aske ſafely and without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, yet is it not our part to appoint the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or meanes, which if we do expreſſe, alwayes a ſecret condition is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded: Therefore was <hi>Paul</hi> heard in the end of
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:3287:79"/>of his prayer, though he had repulſe in the forme of it, &amp;c.</q> Thus M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin;</hi> And what elſe is the contrary, but the ſetting up of mans wiſdom above the wiſdome of God, and our wills above his will? to make our owne choyſe as we thinke good, and to have all our owne way, confining (as it were) the Lord himſelfe by our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory praiers. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing the maine end of our prayers may be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained as well by ſuffering as by doing; and by wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting outward things, aſwel as by enjoying them, wee
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:3287:80"/>are not abſolutely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any exception (at leaſt implied) to offer up our prayers for thoſe things, nor ſo to underſtand the promiſes.</p>
                     <p>To theſe Queſtions and Anſweres hath not the <hi>Temporary</hi> given a word of reſolution, (although they containe the very ſubſtance of the point) perceiving (as it may bee ſuſpected) how they made againſt him; therefore like a good Scholler, hee denyes the concluſion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torting the words upon me, and ſo leaves it.</p>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:3287:80"/>
                     <p>Now there were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe Arguments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in publike, the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of certaine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ſent him in privare, which he hath concealed, returning me then this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwere, that he could not beleeve them. Yet that others who are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to beleeve the truth, may ſee that I am not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in this opinion, I am willing to produce ſome few teſtimonies inſteed of more, to give ſatisfaction; as a ſixt Argument.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 And firſt it appeares to be the Doctrine of the Church of England, for
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:3287:81"/>in the third Homily of Prayer,<note place="margin">It is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of England, &amp; all other Churches of Chriſt.</note> there are theſe words. <hi>Whenſoever wee make our prayers unto God, we are chiefly to reſpect the honour and glory of his name: which thing we ſhall beſt of all doe, if wee follow the example of our<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Saviour</hi> CHRIST, <hi>who praying that the bitter Cupp of Death migh paſſe from him, would not therein have his owne will fulfilled, but referred the whole matter to the good will and pleaſure of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And in the Booke of Common Prayer, there is this forme, <hi>Reſtore to this
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:3287:81"/>ſicke perſon his former health (if it be thy will) or elſe give him grace, &amp;c.</hi> Viſitaſion of the ſicke. Wherin aſwel the ground as the manner of practiſe is diſcovered, and this is and ever hath beene gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally received and taught amongſt us.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 <hi>Vrſinus</hi> on the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Petition layes downe the point at large, how tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things are to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and reſolves that they are to be asked, <hi>With con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the will of God. becauſe the Lord hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them indeterminatly (not expreſsing particulars)
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:3287:82"/>but ſpirituall things may abſolutly be prayed for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſolutely promiſed.</hi> With much more againſt the <hi>Temporaries</hi> opinion, and his unſeemely ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing at the Conditionall <hi>(If)</hi> in the fourth Petition of the Lords prayer. <hi>Vrſin. Catech. pag.</hi> 652.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bucanus</hi> in his learned Inſtitutions handleth the point exactly by way of Queſtion and Anſwere, reſolving the ſame whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to what hath beene ſhewed in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, ſufficient to give any reaſonable man ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. <hi>Bucan. Inſtitut.
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:3287:82"/>Pag.</hi> 673. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Calvine,</hi> and <hi>Gualter</hi> were before cited, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Orthodoxe Tenent of the Reformed Churches abroad.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Doctor <hi>Preſton</hi> and Maſter <hi>Goodwine</hi> of late have ſet downe their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions to the ſame purpoſe. The former in <hi>The Saints dayly Exerciſe, pag.</hi> 99. The latter in his judicious and comfortable Tract of the <hi>Returne of Prayers,</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing theſe words. <q>How didſt thou frame thy prayer for that thing which is denyed thee? Didſt thou pray for it
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:3287:83"/>abſolutely, and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily as ſimply beſt for thee? Thou muſt not then thinke much, if ſuch a prayer bee deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for therein thou wenteſt beyond thy Commiſſion: but if thou didſt pray for it conditionally, and with an <hi>(If)</hi> as Chriſt did, if it bee poſſible, (which Inſtance is a ſtrong ground for ſuch kind of Prayers) and not my will, but thy will bee done, &amp;c: Then thy Prayer may be fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and heard, and yet the thing denyed,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:3287:83"/>&amp;c. <bibl>
                              <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.</bibl>
                        </q> 
                        <hi>And in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place thus:</hi> 
                        <q>All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the promiſe <hi>(of GOD)</hi> to heare and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the prayer bee ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and univerſall, yet the promiſe to heare by granting the very thing it ſelfe prayed for, is but an indefinite pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, wherein we are to rely upon God by an act of recumbencie, though by an act of full aſſurance we cannot, the promiſe being not uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall (<hi>ſpeaking of that in Iam.</hi> 5.) <hi>then addeth,</hi> Of like nature are all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther promiſes of things
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:3287:84"/>outward and temporall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </q>
                        <note place="margin">All deſires in this peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall, If it may ſtand with Gods will &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. So M. <hi>Scudder, pa.</hi> 234.</note> Treating hereof at large in the whole 3. <hi>chap.</hi> whither I referre all ſuch as are willing to bee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfied in the point, for reſolution of the doubts, which elſe I could willingly have tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; but the book is to be had: And of this judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are all that I have ſeene, not to recite any more particulars.</p>
                     <p>By all which teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, the <hi>Temporarie</hi> may perceive how uncouth his opinion is, and in how ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary a way he walketh to defend it, that hath none
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:3287:84"/>to beare him companie, but a few favorites of his own, that admire his deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in this &amp; other things, without any great reaſon. And that wheras he bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleadeth that his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is no other than ſuch as <hi>Moſes, Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and other godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters have taught their congregations heretofore,<note place="margin">If it hath beene ever taught, how is it now raiſed from the dead?</note> which is now againe raiſed from the dead: he diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his underſtanding and faithfulneſſe together in thus ſpeaking; as alſo, his modeſty in maintaining it on ſuch termes as he doth. For thus runs the torrent
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:3287:85"/>of his Language: <hi>Know this for certaine, that as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, &amp; love, and faith is the gift of God, ſo the Lord never gives them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but withall he gives the thing faithed. For if they affirme they have humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and love, and faith, and yet have not the thing fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, they make God a decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, becauſe he never gives the one without the other.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Now our petitions for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things are not agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the will of God, when wee put in this word</hi> (If) <hi>as to ſay, if it be thy wil to give us this or that, but when the thing we deſire is both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:3287:85"/>and promiſed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Come out then, oh thou conditionall from among the petitions of the Lords pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ſit down yonder, thou waſt never placed there by Chriſts appointment, thou haſt robbed God of his glory, thou haſt deprived us of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bleſsings, and a long time lull'd us aſleepe in too much ſecurity, as alſo, blinded us with too much ignorance, &amp;c.</hi> With many the like Paſſages in this diſcourſe, not worth the rehearſall, being full of gall &amp; folly.</p>
                     <p>And heere I ſhould ſhut up all, but that I thinke it expedient to diſcover a
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:3287:86"/>ſtrange diſtinction of faith,<note place="margin">Which I had before noted; <hi>roti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem verbis,</hi> in regard of the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> invented by the <hi>Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> whereon he ſetleth all the building of his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for outward things, and it is this.</p>
                     <p>Wee are to diſtinguiſh Faith into two ſorts:</p>
                     <p>The one is called <hi>Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, or eternall</hi> faith, and ſo called, becauſe the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject it eyeth is of an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall nature, it apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth eternall promiſes.</p>
                     <p>The other is called, <hi>Temporary Faith,</hi> and ſo termed, becauſe the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject it eyeth, is ſome Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall thing, this apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth only Temporall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:3287:86"/>
                     <p>Both which ſorts of faith are required in Gods ſervants, the power of one, to keepe his ſoule to eternall life, the other to provide neceſſaries for the bodie, while God ſhall give this life; for, <hi>The just ſhall live by faith.</hi> Wherin,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. He hath coyned a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction never heard of, in this ſenſe as a <hi>Temporarie faith,</hi> becauſe it hath rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Temporall things. For a Temporarie faith is alwaies, and onely ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, becauſe it laſteth but for a time, in which reſpect our Saviour ſtileth ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,<note place="margin">Non, tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rales, ſed tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarij, in ſpiritualibus.</note> Temporaries,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:3287:87"/>
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 13. and ſo all Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters underſtand the word, ſpeaking of that kind of faith, &amp; ſuch perſons. <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin. Catech.</hi> pag. 104.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. He applieth and in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner confineth) that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>The just ſhall live by faith,</hi> to outward things. Which the Apoſtle uſeth and applieth only to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and ſalvation, and the conco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitants of them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. all; Spirituall matters belonging to that eternall faith, as he calleth it.</p>
                     <p>Thus he muſt needs ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confound himſelfe, or contradict the Scriptures;
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:3287:87"/>for whereas he laboureth to maintaine his diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by alleaging that both thoſe faiths are one in the root, but divers in reſpect of the objects onely: yet ſhould hee not have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted a maine place of Scripture to another ſenſe, then the Holy Ghoſt doth uſe it, by annexing it to that branch of Temporals, by way of Antitheſis: nor yet have formed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſuch a word for the faith of Temporals, as is neither found in Scripture, nor any good Author. Yet he is ſo confident, as to go on, and conclude in this
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:3287:88"/>manner: <hi>So now you ſee (notwithſtanding your great ſtir) the diſtinction being grounded on the Word of God, remaineth unmoueable.</hi> Suppoſing (it ſeemes) his diſtinction to be like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, upon the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of ſuch a ground.</p>
                     <p>And this I have the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſiſted upon, that it may appeare to his admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, how confident &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory he is in his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and upon how weak grounds, that they may beware of him in other things aſwell as in this. For my part, I bear much ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and reproach fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:3287:88"/>being foule and injurious in his language; all which I refer unto the Lord, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting my ſelfe unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to ſuffer rebuke for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie part of his Truth. Wiſhing unto him more modeſtie &amp; humilitie, and then (no doubt) he would be more Orthodox, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the promiſe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25 9. <hi>The meek wil he guide in judgement, the meek will he teach his way.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> 
                        <hi>Exhortation</hi> to all that depend upon <hi>God,</hi> to aske ſuch things at his hands as are expedient for them, as <hi>Agur</hi> did, without deſiring abundance, which doth
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:3287:89"/>but enſnare the owners, as experience ſhewes: and herein to take the written word of <hi>God</hi> for a rule, what is lawfull or unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be asked, whether it concerne the <hi>life, goods, eſtate, maintenance, ſucceſs of our ſelues or others;</hi> and withall to ſubmit to his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret will and pleaſure for the diſpoſing or beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame, as it ſhall ſeeme beſt to his <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> for the glory of his name, and our owne good, reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our ſelves wholly thereunto, and beleeving aſſuredly that what is beſt ſhall be done unto us, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:3287:89"/>to his infinite wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and providence; therefore in al our praiers, if not expreſly (which is not abſolutly neceſſary,) yet implicitely to include the ſame, and then wee ſhall be ſure to pray accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will, and our Prayers ſhall not bee in vaine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Nilergo optabunt ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>es? ſi e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>ſilium vis,</l>
                           <l>Permittes ipſis ex pendere n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>inibus, quid</l>
                           <l>Conveniat nobis, rebuſque ſit utile noſtris.</l>
                           <l>Nam pro jucundis aptiſſima quaeque dabunt dij.</l>
                           <l>Charior eſtillis homo, quàm ſibi; nos animorum</l>
                           <l>Impulſiu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; caeca magnaque cupidine ducti</l>
                           <l>Cori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>am peri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </l>
                           <l>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>, qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap>.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <bibl>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>. Sat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </bibl>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3287:90"/>
                  <p>AN Advertiſement concerning <hi>TRASKISME.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As a Parallel to the <hi>Former.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:3287:90"/>
                  <head>Of M. TRASKE, <hi>and his Opinions.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Trask</hi> ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine yeares ſince was juſtly cenſured in a High Court of this Land, for <hi>Iudaiſme,</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant errours, it is ſo that not long after, he fell (the cauſe in himſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining) into contrary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities,<note place="margin">Dum ſtulti vitant vitia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> &amp;c.</note> of Evangelicall pretenſe, under the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhewes and names of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> of the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:3287:91"/>
                     <hi>Goſpel,</hi> of <hi>Ioy,</hi> and ſuch like alluring titles; thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hiding, and ſecretly venting many pernicious errours,<note place="margin">* Rom. 16.18. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> to the endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of none of the worſt people, and of late is growne to a great extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie herein. I deſire (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by <hi>God</hi>'s Providence made acquainted with the ſame) if leave may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven (which heereby I crave) to diſcover and publiſh ſome of his chiefe Aſſertions and Grounds, that whereſoever they are mett withall, their owner (who lyes hid) may bee knowne,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>As,</hi> Ex vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onem.</note> and ſo the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:3287:91"/>armed againſt the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill, and they are theſe following:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Law is a rule of the fleſh, and to live after the Law, is to live after the Fleſh.</hi> Rom. 8.1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The errour of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinominant</hi> &amp; <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>The Lawe is not to bee preached to Beleevers by Goſpell Miniſters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If Repentance and Faith bee wrought onely by the Goſpell, then what doth the Law worke in any mans converſion to God, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Law did once diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſinne,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See contrary <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7.</note> it doth ſo no more, nor yet for direction; Love herein tranſcends the Law;
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:3287:92"/>as far as Life doth Death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Then we are Iuſtified by a qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>The New Covenant hath no condition at all, Faith is not the Condition of the Goſpells promiſes, but onely a qualification in us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">This is only true of the Law. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15.</note>The Goſpell was in mans Nature before the Fall.</p>
                  <p>Faith is not to bee tried by any fruits or effects, but onely by the perſwaſion it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Every ſaving grace is a ſigne. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.14.</note>Faith is the onely ſigne of Salvation.</p>
                  <p>The new Creature is onely Faith in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Regeneration is not to be tryed, by any other fruits, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, or ſignes, but onely by Faith, wherein it conſiſts.</p>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:3287:92"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iuſtification and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded.</note>Sanctification is not by the Spirit in our ſelves, but onely in Chriſt, ſhewed in acts and not in the habits of grace.</p>
                  <p>Beleevers when they fall into any ſinne,<note place="margin">This touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon the Familiſts.</note> be it Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or Murther, are not to mourne nor grieve (for that ſavours of the fleſh) but ſtill to rejoice, becauſe it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, rejoyce evermore, and that joy is the ſpecial meanes to bring them out of their ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> is not oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</note>Careleſſe Chriſtians are the choiſeſt beleevers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they depend wholly upon Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>To doubt of the favour of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:3287:93"/>God after ſinne committed, is worſe then the ſin it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudas</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, but beleeved not</note>It is as eaſie to beleeve re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſins, as to make confeſsion of them.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt is involved in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Proverb of <hi>Salomon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>15.</hi> Pſalme is onely a deſcription of Chriſt, and the beatitudes, <hi>Math. 5.</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belong to him, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> man that ever was, or would be, bee: all men are vanity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Chriſt is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the wiſe, but to the Husband.</note>The ſaying of <hi>Salomon,</hi> rejoyce in the wife of thy youth, is not meant of a mans wife, but of Chriſt, becauſe he can ſatisfy us at all times.</p>
                  <p>It is two great preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for any Miniſter to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:3287:93"/>the Expoſition of any whol Book in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;<note place="margin">Therefore he holds that which he cannot ſhew.</note> becauſe hee cannot ſhew how Chriſt is invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in every pert.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> left their firſt love. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4.</note>Every true Believer (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it ſeemes) doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies grow in faith &amp; love, and anſwerable fruits.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Then, no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving man can ſay that he loveth his brother</note>No man can ſay hee doth love his Brother, till he hath laid downe his life for him. Neither can wee ſay our ſelves, that we love the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but wee may ſay of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that they doe, ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding <hi>1 John 3.14.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee calleth this,</hi> The glorious way;<note place="margin">[The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject] ſo he writes.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſtileth himſelfe,</hi> The Subject in
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:3287:94"/>whom the Lord delighteth to work through Christ.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THeſe are the Flowers of his Garden, diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed abroad in Print, and Writings, and by word of mouth wherby he hath la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to ſeduce the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which I think ſufficiet only to mention for their abſurdity, an anſwer being too much credit to them, although the moſt of them are already</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">By Maſter <hi>Hynd,</hi> Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> in his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula vita,</hi> at large.</note> 
                     <hi>anſwered, in publike and private, onely I think it expedient to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe the Reader, and all that have to deale with him, of five things:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1. That they give no
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:3287:94"/>heed to any Catalogue of his Goſpell grounds, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee hath publiſhed many of contrary quality, in divers particulars, one croſſing another, as thus:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Believers do alwaies grow in faith and love, and the exerciſe of all pious duties.</p>
                  <p>A man may be a Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and for a time have neither humilitie, love, truſt, nor any other grace bud forth in practice.</p>
                  <p>The Law ſheweth what man ſhould doe.</p>
                  <p>The Law is not the rule of Life. <hi>With many ſuch.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2. That they take no great heed to his interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:3287:95"/>of Scripture, for that hee will ſuddenly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, as many ſenſes as will ſerve his turne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3. That they credit not eaſily his Proteſtations, or Denials, becauſe therin he hath been found moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull, and falſe, witneſs one for all, in a Letter:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>st before God, who knoweth all, and before <hi>JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST,</hi> the Iudge of all, that I hold no other but that one Goſpell which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> wrote of; the Lord Ieſus, and his Apoſtles Preached; the Martyrs witneſſed; our King defendeth; our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>h and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:3287:95"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A fearfull Proteſtation, yet how true, the former aſſertions declare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4. To beware of his Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, for when hee would hide his Error, he will turn it into a Riddle; as thus:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They would have the Law to be a Rule of life, to ſuch as know it in the infinit holineſſe of it, the vaile being removed from their hearts, as they dare thinke on no righteouſneſſe by it at all, but onely in and by Ieſus Chriſt. — <hi>Againe,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Law hath nothing at all to do with Believers, but they have moſt of all to doe with the Law, &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:3287:96"/>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5. To beware of his fawning by which hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth, but chiefly his pride through which hee erreth, and dares to abuſe the holy Scriptures as hee doth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And thus recommending alſo this diſery to the care of every Chriſtian, for his owne ſafety, that he may try the Spirits before hee receive them, and not run under the curſe of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, or venting</hi> New Goſpels,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> 
                     <hi>I end with this advertiſement,</hi> That the Spirit of regeneration, is a Spirit of Truth. <hi>Ioh. 3.5.14.17.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <p>Ventri ſervire, &amp; blandè loqui, ſeu aſſentari; duae ſunt notae Pſendo Apoſtolorum.</p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pet. Mart.</hi> in <hi>Rom. 16.18.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3287:96"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
